Finding Aid for the Ferdinand Praeger Collection of Scores, circa 1829-1891
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
- Vocal works, 1829-1891, V.; Item 430-476
  - Solo songs, 1829-1890, A.; Item 430-466
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Après tant de jours: Chastelard's song / [18--], 1 ms. score ([1] p.); 35 cm.; Alternate title: Chastelard's song (Box 14, Item 433)
      For medium voice and piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Sung by the character Chastelard in Act I, scene ii in Swinburne's tragedy, Chastelard.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Chanson Chastelard / [18--], 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: Navire est à l'eau (Box 14, Item 434)
      For medium voice and piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Sung by the character Mary Beaton in Act I, scene i in Swinburne's tragedy, Chastelard.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Convivial song / [18--], 1 ms. score ([1] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: If you will gain old age (Box 14, Item 435)
      For medium voice and piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink).
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Deception / [18--], 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: We thought the world so full of smiles (Box 14, Item 436)
      For medium voice and piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Correction on insert pasted on p. [2].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. The dying child's request: song / [18--], 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: And when you see that I am dead (Box 14, Item 437)
      For medium voice and piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Right side of p. [1] torn.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Einz'ger Trost / [18--], 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 35 cm.; First line of text: Es seutzt im Schilf wie Herzens weh (Box 14, Item 438)
      For high voice and piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink).
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. England's shore: national song / [18--], 1 ms. score ([4] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: Let others praise be foreign land (Box 15, Item 439)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Es kam ein Knappe aus fernem Land Romanze aus der Oper die Bergknappen / [18--], 1 ms. score ([4] p.); 30 cm.; First line of text: Es kam ein Knappe aus fernem Land (Box 15, Item 440)
      For voice and piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Text from Act I, scene vii of Theodor Körner's libretto Die Bergknappen. Above vocal line: Walther. Some instrument names indicated throughout the piano line. Corrections on inserts pasted throughout.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Frühlingslied / [18--], 1 ms. score (8 p.); 30 cm.; First line of text: Frühling ich grüsse dich (Box 15, Item 441)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. If thou wer't but my own / [18--], 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: If thou wer't but my own (Box 15, Item 442)
      For medium voice and piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink).
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Laub und Lust / 1844, 1 ms. score ([6] p.); 31 cm. (Box 15, Item 443)
      For high voice and piano. Caption title (difficult to decipher, possibly incorrect). Holograph (Ink). Incomplete work. Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [1]; other corrections made in pencil. Caption: London July 1844.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Lieb Liebchen legs Händchen / [18--], 1 ms. score (7 p.); 31 cm.; Alternate title: Lieb Liebchen legs Händchen aufs Herr (Box 15, Item 444)
      For medium voice and piano. Manuscript (Ink). "und Fraulein Armbruster freundschaftlich gewidmet"--Caption.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Lied / [18--], 1 ms. score ([4] p.); 31 cm. (Box 15, Item 445)
      For medium voice and piano. Caption title. Indecipherable song text. Holograph (Ink). Incomplete work. Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [2].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Lied der Spinnerin / [1844], 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: Schnurre, schnurre, meine Spindel (Box 15, Item 446)
      For high voice and piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: 1844.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Love at first sight / [18--], 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 35 cm.; First line of text: I saw and loved her at first sight (Box 15, Item 447)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Love's sympathy: song / [18--], 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 30 cm.; First line of text: Why must she be the only one (Box 15, Item 448)
      For medium voice and piano. Caption title. Manuscript (Ink).
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Man's inconstancy / 1843, 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 30 cm.; First line of text: Dream not of love (Box 15, Item 449)
      For medium voice and piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: London 2 January 1843.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Mary Beaton's song: [from] Chastelar[d] / [18--], 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 35 cm.; First line of text: Between the sunset and the sea (Box 15, Item 450)
      For medium voice and piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Sung by the character Mary Beaton in Act I, scene ii in Swinburne's tragedy, Chastelard.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Mein Liebchen hat mich verlassen: Volkslied / [18--], 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 35 cm.; First line of text: Mein Liebchen die hat mich verlassen (Box 15, Item 451)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Mein Liebchen hat mich verlassen / [18--], 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 31 cm. (Box 15, Item 452)
      For medium voice and piano. German words. Title from first line of text. Holograph (Ink); p. [3] in pencil. Incomplete work.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Mitternacht / 1844, 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 31 cm. (Box 15, Item 453)
      For medium voice and piano. Caption title (difficult to decipher, possibly incorrect). Holograph (Ink). Incomplete work. Caption: Juny 1844.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. O sweet to my soul is that beautiful grove / [18--], 1 ms. score ([6] p.); 30 cm. (Box 15, Item 454)
      For high voice and piano. Title from first line of text. Text from a stanza of the poem "Bolehill trees" by James Montgomery. Holograph (Ink).
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. The reefer's song / [18--], 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 24 x 30 cm.; First line of text: Far away far away on the billow (Box 15, Item 455)
      For medium voice and piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: Prize composition. "Motto: After a storm cometh a calm"--Caption.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Remember: song / 1890, 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: Remember me when I am gone away (Box 15, Item 456)
      For medium voice and piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: Oct. 90.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Schlummerlied / [18--], 1 ms. score ([4] p.); 37 cm.; First line of text: Es ruht die Welt in Abendduft (Box 15, Item 457)
      For medium voice and piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: Februar 1888.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. The secret / [18--], 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: Could I my secret but reveal (Box 15, Item 458)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. [Song cycle for medium voice and piano] / [18--], 1 ms. score ([11] p.); 30-35 cm. (Box 15, Item 459)
      For medium voice and piano. Texts not present. Title supplied by cataloger. Holograph (Ink). Songs 1-10 were received in the same folder. Song 11 was originally listed as a violin and piano work in the Finkelman inventory and song 12 (War song) was received in a separate folder, but both appear to belong to this set.
      Contents: Ballad song (Very moderate) [G major] -- Song (Slowly) [G major] -- Song (Very slowly, dreamily) [A♭ major] -- Song (Moderate time) [E♭ major] -- Ballad (Allegretto) [G major] -- Song (Very slowly) [E♭ major] -- Ballad (Moderate) [F major] -- Song (Lively with emotion) [E♭ major] -- Ballad (With spirit) [G major] -- Song (Slowly, gracefully) [F major] -- War song or military ditty (Moderato) [F major].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Song of Mary, Queen of Scots :[from] Chastelard / [18--], 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: J'ai vu faner bien des choses (Box 15, Item 460)
      For medium voice and piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Sung by the character Mary, Queen of Scots in Act II, scene i in Swinburne's tragedy, Chastelard.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. The song of the past / [18--], 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: You ask me as I used to sing a homely friendly lay (Box 15, Item 461)
      For medium voice and piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Corrections on inserts pasted on p. [2].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Selections Das Standchen von Uhland: National lied; Tempo di Bolero; Im Style Russischer national Lieder / 1840, 1 ms. score ([6] p.); 30 cm. (Box 15, Item 462)
      First work for voice and piano, second work for piano, third work possibly for violin and piano, fourth work for voice and piano. German words. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Third and fourth works are incomplete. Caption, p. 1: August 1839; p. 4: April 28/1840; p. 5: 22 May 1839, 26 May 1839; p. 6: 29 Dec. 1840.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Die Todtenuhr =the deathwatch / 1842, 1 ms. score ([5] p.); 30 cm.; First line of text: Die Mitternachts Stunde ertönt vom Thurm (Box 15, Item 463)
      For medium voice and piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: 12 July 1842.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Traurige Liebe / [18--], 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 35 cm.; First line of text: Ach, Könnt ich dir nur sagen (Box 15, Item 464)
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. T'was but in dreams / [18--], 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: T'was but in dreams that happines e'er came to me (Box 15, Item 465)
      For medium voice and piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Corrections in manuscript pasted on p. [1, 2].
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. [Untitled song in A major] / 1829, 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 30 cm. (Box 15, Item 466)
      For medium voice and piano. Title supplied by cataloger. Indecipherable song text. Holograph (Ink). Caption: London 19th November 1829. "für das Emil"--Caption.
  - Duets, 1888-1891, B.; Item 467-472
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Come back: duet for soprano and contralto / 1888, 1 ms. score ([5] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: Come back, come back, ye friendships long departed (Box 15, Item 467)
      For soprano, alto, and piano. Cover title. Text from Henry Wadsworth Longfellow's poem "The golden legend". Holograph (Ink). Cover: 5th Sept. 1888.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Come back Duet from the Golden legend / 1888, 1 ms. score ([5] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: Come back, come back, ye friendships long departed (Box 15, Item 468)
      For soprano, alto, and piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: Sept 88. "The words from: The Golden Legend by Longfellow, Duet for soprano & contralto"--Caption.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Daybreak: duet for soprano and contralto / 1888, 1 ms. score ([5] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: A wind came up out of the sea (Box 15, Item 469)
      For soprano, alto, and piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). At end of piece: 22/9/88.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. May morning: duet for soprano and contralto / 1888, 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: Now the bright morning star (Box 15, Item 470)
      For soprano, alto, and piano. Cover title. Manuscript (Ink). Cover: Septr 1888.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. May morning / 1891, 1 ms. score ([3] p.); 31 cm.; First line of text: Now the bright morning star (Box 15, Item 471)
      For soprano, alto, and piano. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Caption: 1891.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. The stars are with the voyager: duet for soprano and contralto / 1888, 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 31 cm. (Box 15, Item 472)
      For soprano, alto, and piano. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Cover: Septr. 1888.
  - Part-songs and choruses, undated, C.; Item 473-474
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Spring: part-song for four female voices / [18--], 1 ms. score (5 p.) + 4 ms. parts; 31 cm.; First line of text: Spring forecasts its magic spell (Box 15, Item 473)
      For 2 sopranos and 2 altos. Cover title. Manuscript (Ink).
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Tell me my lute: serenade from Sheridan's Duenna / [18--], 1 ms. score ([9] p.); 35 cm. (Box 15, Item 474)
      For 2 tenors and 2 basses. Cover title. Holograph (Ink). Paper is extremely fragile.
  - Opera excerpts, 1837-1890, D.; Item 475-476
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Brascovano. Vocal score. Selections Brascovano / 1890, 1 ms. score ([60] p.); 31 cm. (Box 15, Item 475)
      Opera. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Incomplete work. In caption, p. [16]: 29/4 90; p. [17]: 23/4 90; p. [50]: 1 May 90; p. [60]: 3/12 90.
      Contents: Overture -- National songs -- Valse sentimentale -- Turkish march -- Turkish drinking song -- Chorus of Turkish soldiers -- Quartet -- Constantine's story -- Chorus -- Trio -- Pas seul -- Song Helena -- Song Michaela -- Song Helena (Moderato) -- Vocal duet.
    - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Gustav Wasa. Selections; arr. [Selections from] Gustav Wasa :heroische Oper / 1837, 1 ms. piano score ([8] p.); 31 cm. (Box 15, Item 476)
      Opera. Caption title. Holograph (Ink). Possibly an incomplete vocal score; no text is present. Correction on insert pasted on p. [2]. "Copied from an old mspt of 1837, one of my youthful operas. F. Praeger"--left margin. Caption: 1842.
      Contents: Chor (Maestoso) -- Chor (Allegro moderato) -- Lieges marsch -- Hymnus -- Lied -- Romance -- March & chorus -- March -- Lied (Molto moderato).
- Sketches and fragments, 1842-1889, VI.; Item 477-479
  This series contains two sketchbooks and other miscellaneous sketches and fragments. These items were placed in folders in the groupings in which they were received.
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Manuscript music book, 1848, [24] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 16, Item 477)
    Sketches for various instrumentations. Cover title. Holograph (Ink); some sketches in pencil. Corrections on inserts pasted throughout.
    Contents: Ballade sentimentale -- Ballad [in E♭ major] -- Elegy -- Air nationale -- Choral -- String quartet -- Ballad -- Trio for strings [in] E minor -- Valse sentimentale -- Etude de tristesse -- Scherzo -- Cavatina.
  - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Manuscript music book, 1854-1878, [24] p. of ms. music; 35 cm. (Box 16, Item 478)
    Contents: Piano concerto -- Savoyardenlied -- Sonata 8 -- Klavier Konzert -- Quartett in G -- 6th sonata in E-flat -- Nocturne-adagio -- Introduction -- Piano trio or concerto.
  - Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891. Unidentified musical sketches and fragments, [1842-1889], 1 folder (17 items). (Box 16, Item 479)
    Sketches for various and unknown instrumentations. Placed in folders in groupings as received. Title supplied by cataloger. Holograph (Ink); some sketches in pencil. Some sketches have corrections on inserts pasted throughout. Dated sketches range from 1842-1889; many sketches are undated.
    Contents: [1]. Andante (1 leaf) -- [2]. Caption: Re-engrave from A to B (final page numbered 13) -- [3]. Allegro moderato (1 leaf; colophon: 86 bars) -- [4]. Moderato, continued by Poco meno mosso (2 pages) -- [5]. No. 3, No. 4, No. 5, No. 6 (4 pages) -- [6]. Ben pronunziato la melodia (2 leaves) -- [7]. Allegro molto, 10 April 89 (1 leaf) -- [8]. Für Violins, 10 Decr. 1844 (4 pages) -- [9]. Sonata in G [for] violin and piano: Scherzo (2 leaves) -- [10]. Untitled work with solo line above grand staff in 9/8 meter (2 pages) -- [11]. Album leaf: Quartett: Fairy scherzo, 23 Aug. 87 (1 oblong leaf) -- [12]. Pages 25-29 of untitled orchestral work (5 oblong pages) -- [13]. Andantino for two violins, viola, violoncello, and contrabass (1 leaf) -- [14]. Three untitled leaves: two pencil manuscripts and one ink oblong -- [15]. Untitled ink manuscript on grand staff (2 pages) -- [16]. Untitled pieces 1: Andante (5 March 1842), 2: Vivace, 3: Cantabile (11 March 1842), 4 (30 July 1842) (4 pages) -- [17]. 1 folder of loose fragments, including a manuscript with figured bass markings.
- Documents, 1882-1892, VII.; Item 480-484
  This series contains a small number of non-musical documents related to Praeger.
  - Agreement with the Earl of Dysart / [1888], [1] p.; 33 cm. (Box 16, Item 480)
    Specifies that Praeger is to send compositions to the Earl of Dysart quarterly for 12 years, beginning on Mar. 1, 1890. Signed by J.A. Bertram, Esq.
  - Folder for delivery of compositions to the Earl of Dysart / 1892, [1] p.; 33 cm. (Box 16, Item 481)
    Front of folder: 2d Grand Symphonic Poem in F for full orchestra. Received housing Legend for winds. Specifies two dates of delivery in accordance with the agreement with the Earl of Dysart. Signed by B.L. Mosely, Ferdinand Praeger, H.J. Edwards, and Lilian Grace Mary Blyth.
  - Fleeting thoughts wrappers / [1882-1885], 3 folders.; 23 cm. (Box 16, Item 482)
    Each folder reads: Eight "Fleeting Thoughts" by Ferdinand Praeger. Each folder was received housing eight of the Fleeting thoughts piano pieces. The dates of these pieces range from 1882-1885.
  - Ferdinand Praeger's address cards / [18--], 4 cards; 4 x 8 cm. (Box 16, Item 483)
    4 copies, reading: Mr. Ferdinand Praeger, Lansdowne, 23 Brackenbury Road, Shepherds Bush, W. One has note: Same house as 4 Bradmore Park Terrace.
  - Leaf from an auction house or bookseller's catalog / [19--], [2] p.; 20 cm. (Box 16, Item 484)
    Under Music heading, lot 515: Praeger, Ferdinand, MS- Large collection of original compositions. Bottom of page torn, rest of description is missing.
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Subjects
Music--Manuscripts; Praeger, Ferdinand, 1815-1891--Manuscripts
Genres
Holographs (autographs); Manuscripts (document genre); Scores
Associated Material
Bibliography
Hutchinson, Clare Lucille. The musical and literary manuscripts of Ferdinand Praeger (1815-1891) in the Moldenhauer Archives Ph.D. diss. Indiana University, 1969.
Ryberg, James Stanley. Four string quartets by Ferdinand Praeger: an analytical study Ph.D. diss. Northwestern University, 1978.
Additional Guides
All scores in the collection are cataloged in WorldCat and are available in BISON, the online catalog for the University at Buffalo Libraries, by performing a "Title begins with" search under "Ferdinand Praeger Collection of Scores".
The previous inventory of the collection, compiled by M. Finkelman in 1985, may be found in the Music Library collection with the call number ML 410 P789 AXF5. This inventory lists the items in a different order than the current arrangement and does not include all items in the collection. It can also be seen online.
Related Resources
Other collections of Ferdinand Praeger's Manuscripts
Moldenhauer Archives, Northwestern University
Northwestern University holds manuscripts of both musical and literary works by Ferdinand Praeger. Their holdings can be viewed by clicking the link above and performing a "Title" search for "Praeger, Ferdinand".
British Library
The British Library holds approximately 93 manuscripts of Praeger's works, most of which are for piano. Their holdings can be viewed by accessing their main catalog through the link above and searching for "Praeger, Ferdinand".
List of digitized Praeger family documents courtesy of Ferdinand Praeger's great-great-grandson Andrew Leach.
A list of several documents, photographs, and a portrait of Ferdinand Praeger. Digital copies of items in the possession of Ferdinand Praeger's great-great-grandson Andrew Leach.